<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compositeCheatsheet name="HelloWorld">
   <taskGroup kind="set" name="Composite cheat sheet example" skip="false">
      <intro>
         This is an example of a <b>composite cheat sheet</b> built from existing cheat sheets.
                 <br/><br/>You can select a task to work on either by following the hyperlinks or by
                 selecting a task in the tree.
      </intro>
      <onCompletion>
         Congratulations you have completed all the tasks.
      </onCompletion>
      <task kind="cheatsheet" name="Branching and merging using CVS" skip="true">
         <intro>
            This cheat sheet is intended for CVS users. If you are not using CVS or do
              not intend to branch and merge you may skip this task.
         </intro>
         <onCompletion>
            Congratulations you now know how to branch and merge.
         </onCompletion>
         <param name="id" value="org.eclipse.platform.cvs_1">
         </param>
         <param name="path" value="HelloWorldModel.xml">
         </param>
      </task>
      <taskGroup kind="sequence" name="Create Java Projects" skip="false">
         <intro>
            First you will learn how to create a simple java project, then you will create 
             an java project which uses SWT. 
             <br/><br/>This task group is a sequence which means that
             if you click on the subtask &quot;Standalone SWT Application&quot; it will not let that task be started 
             until &quot;Create a java project&quot; has been completed.
         </intro>
         <onCompletion>
            Congratulations you have built both Java applications.
         </onCompletion>
         <task id="createJavaProject" kind="cheatsheet" name="Create a java project" skip="false">
            <intro>
               This cheat sheet walks through the process of creating a simple hello world application. 
                        The cheat sheet can launch wizards to create a new project and a new class.
            </intro>
            <onCompletion>
               Congratulations you have succeeded in creating a hello world application
            </onCompletion>
            <param name="id" value="org.eclipse.jdt.helloworld">
            </param>
            <param name="showIntro" value="false">
            </param>
         </task>
         <task kind="cheatsheet" name="Standalone SWT Application" skip="false">
            <intro>
               Eclipse plugins which contribute to the user interface use The Standard Widget Toolkit (SWT). 
                    This task guide can be used to learn more about SWT.
            </intro>
            <onCompletion>
               Congratulations you have succeeded in creating an SWT application.
            </onCompletion>
            <param name="id" value="org.eclipse.jdt.helloworld.swt">
            </param>
         </task>
         <taskGroup kind="set" name="Another Group" skip="false">
            <intro>
               <b>Introduction</b>
            </intro>
            <onCompletion>
               <b>Conclusion</b>
            </onCompletion>
            <task kind="cheatsheet" name="The only Task I have" skip="false">
               <intro>
                  <b>Introduction</b>
               </intro>
               <onCompletion>
                  <b>Conclusion</b>
               </onCompletion>
            </task>
         </taskGroup>
      </taskGroup>
   </taskGroup>
</compositeCheatsheet>
