<!-- 
  UK Crown Copyright (c) 2016. All Rights Reserved
-->
<!-- Converted by db4-upgrade version 1.0 -->
<preface xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="preface"><info><title>Preface</title></info>

<para>
This tutorial is not an introduction to programming but an overall description
of programming in <abbrev>MASL</abbrev><xref linkend="MASL06"/>. It is assumed
that the reader will have significant experience of programming in some high
level language, along with knowledge of Shlaer-Mellor OOA modelling
(<xref linkend="Shlaer88"/>, 
<xref linkend="Shlaer92"/> and
<xref linkend="Mellor02"/>).
</para>
<para>
In <xref linkend="Types"/>, we introduce the notion of declaration and
assignment together with the ideas of scope and visibility.
The important concepts of type, subtype and constraints are then explained.
The remainder of this chapter discusses some of the specific and general types
in <abbrev>MASL</abbrev>.
</para>
<para>
In <xref linkend="ExecutionControl"/> we learn about the main sequential control
structures of <abbrev>MASL</abbrev>.
<xref linkend="CompositeTypes"/> continues from where
<xref linkend="Types"/> left off, by describing the more complex types of
<abbrev>MASL</abbrev>.
<xref linkend="Exceptions"/> describes the use of exceptions and exception
handling.
In <xref linkend="ObjectsandRelationships"/> we finally get to the main use
of <abbrev>OOA</abbrev>, and describe how instances of objects are created,
found and deleted. In addition, this section discusses how we create, navigate
and delete relationships between these instances.
In <xref linkend="Actions"/> we discuss actions, which are the places where
statements, together with appropriate declarations, that encapsulate a set
of processes are held.
Finally, in <xref linkend="DeviceIO"/> we discuss how to read and write data to
and from devices and files.
This tutorial is a companion to the MASL Reference Manual
<xref linkend="MASL06"/>, which should be
referenced for a completion language description.
</para>
</preface>
